<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: workshop | ]]></title>
  <link href="/categories/workshop/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-28T13:35:04-08:00</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="https://github.com/recurser/jekyll-plugins">Recurser</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Digital Humanities Skills Workshop]]></title>
    <link href="/workshop/2016/01/12/dh-skills-workshop/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>/workshop/2016/01/12/dh-skills-workshop</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As part of Digital Humanities: Asia, Nicole Coleman and Jason Heppler are running a series of workshops at the Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis. If you are interested in learning more about Digital Humanities tools and techniques or want to prepare for the upcoming DHAsia workshops (<a href="http://dhasia.org/">http://dhasia.org/</a>), bring a laptop and dig into the following sessions co-sponsored by CIDR, CESTA, and the DH Focal Group.</p>

<p>All sessions will be held at CESTA in rm 433A unless otherwise specified.</p>

<h3>DATA WRANGLING WITH PYTHON</h3>

<p>David McClure, a developer at the Library&#39;s Center for Interdisciplinary Digital Research, will teach a two- part workshop to introduce techniques for cleaning and managing messy data with Python.
If you are interested in using Python for network analysis, you may be interested in the NetworkX workshop on 2/15.</p>

<p>Part 1: Monday, January 11, 2 p.m. - 4 p.m.</p>

<p>Part 2: Monday, January 25, 2 p.m. - 4 p.m.</p>

<h3>OMEKA</h3>

<p>Jason Heppler, the ATS for History and member of CIDR will get you up and running with Omeka (<a href="http://omeka.org/">http://omeka.org/</a>) an open source platform for digital publishing and exhibit building. If you are interested in Neatline, this workshop will familiarize you with the underlying platform.
Thursday, January 14, 2 p.m. - 4 p.m.</p>

<h3>NEATLINE</h3>

<p>David McClure, one of the Neatline developers and now part of the CIDR team in the Library will take you through the process of building an interactive spatial and temporal exhibit with Neatline (<a href="http://neatline.org/">http://neatline.org/</a>), a set of add on tools for Omeka. (See the 1/14 Omeka workshop above.)
Monday, February 1, 2 p.m.- 4 p.m.</p>

<h3>PALLADIO</h3>

<p>The Digital Humanities Focal Group is hosting this introduction to Palladio, a suite of visualization tools for data exploration. (<a href="http://palladio.designhumanities.org">http://palladio.designhumanities.org</a>) This workshop will take place in Building 260, Room 252.</p>

<p>Monday, January 25, 12:00-1:30 p.m.</p>

<h3>NETWORKS</h3>

<p>The introductory session in this two-part series will show you how to prepare a data set for network analysis and then visualize that data set with Gephi and/or Cytoscape. We will also share examples of network analysis in humanities research. The second session, taught by Sebastian Ahnert, will provide an introduction to the Python package for network analysis, NetworkX. If you are not familiar with Python, the sessions taught by Dave McClure beginning January 11 will prepare you for this session.
Part 1, Introduction to Networks for Humanists: Monday, February 8, 2 p.m. - 4 p.m.
Part 2, Network Analysis and NetworkX: Monday, February 22, 2 p.m. - 4 p.m.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>