<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: News | ]]></title>
  <link href="/categories/news/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="/"/>
  <updated>2016-02-02T15:45:35-08:00</updated>
  <id>/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="https://github.com/recurser/jekyll-plugins">Recurser</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[]]></title>
    <link href="/news/2013/10/08/657/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/news/2013/10/08/657</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://cesta.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/TheBlackBardPoster_3.png"><img class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-663" title="TheBlackBardPoster_3" src="https://cesta.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/TheBlackBardPoster_3.png" alt="" width="240" height="317" /></a></p>

<p>Please join us for our first *CESTA Presents *event of the new school year:</p>

<div>
  <span style="font-size: large;"><strong>Cecil Brown<br /> <em>George Moses Horton Slave Poet and Hip-Hop Prototype</em></strong><br /> </span>
</div>

<div>
  <span style="font-size: large;"><strong>Thursday, October 10th, 1 PM</strong></span>
</div>

<div>
  <span style="font-size: large;"><strong>Wallenberg Hall (Building 160)</strong></span>
</div>

<div>
  <strong><span style="font-size: large;">Fourth Floor, Room 433A</span><br /> </strong>
</div>

<div>
</div>

<div>
  Professor Cecil Brown (U C Berkeley scholar) will lecture on George Moses Horton, an African American slave poet, who lived from 1798 to 1883. Professor Brown maintains that Digital Humanities can reveal the hidden treasures of one of the most brilliant poets of Early American Culture.</p>
</div>

<p>Event is free and open to the public &#8211; please pass this announcement along to anyone who might be interested.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Humanities + Design Receives NEH Grant!]]></title>
    <link href="/news/2013/08/20/humanities-design-receives-neh-grant/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/news/2013/08/20/humanities-design-receives-neh-grant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<div id="center">
  <div id="post-28825">
    <h2>
      Stanford digital humanities researchers receive NEH grant
    </h2>

    <div>
      August 19th, 2013
    </div>

    <div>
      <p>
        <a href="http://news.stanford.edu/thedish/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Mapping-6.jpg"><img src="http://news.stanford.edu/thedish/wp-content/uploads/2013/08/Mapping-6-568x379.jpg" alt="Mapping-6" width="568" height="379" /></a>
      </p>

      <p>
        <a href="http://news.stanford.edu/thedish/?p=28825" target="_blank">Humanities+Design at Stanford</a>
      </p>

      <p>
        A grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH) will enable Stanford researchers to develop a suite of network visualization tools specifically designed for humanities research.
      </p>

      <p>
        <strong><a href="http://republicofletters.stanford.edu/people/index.html">DAN EDELSTEIN</a></strong>, an associate professor of French, and history Professor <strong><a href="http://history.stanford.edu/findlen_paula">PAULA FINDLEN</a></strong> are the principal investigators of “Networks in History,” which was awarded nearly $300,000 from the NEH.
      </p>

      <p>
        The grant will allow Edelstein, Findlen and their colleagues to build on visualization tools they developed for <a href="http://republicofletters.stanford.edu/">Mapping the Republic of Letters</a>, a Stanford digital humanities endeavor that is using technology to analyze the circulation of people, letters and objects during the 17th and 18th centuries.
      </p>

      <p>
        Drawing from an array of digitized materials from the Stanford University Libraries, Oxford University, Bibliotheque National de France, Centre National de la Recherché Scientifique and other archives around the globe, Mapping the Republic of Letters projects have given scholars new perspectives on the social networks that connected the intellectuals of the European Enlightenment.
      </p>

      <p>
        A scholar of 18th-century French history and literature, Edelstein has been using metadata provided by the Electronic Enlightenment Project at Oxford University to situate <a href="http://republicofletters.stanford.edu/casestudies/voltaire/index.html">Voltaire’s correspondence network</a> within the broader Enlightenment Republic of Letters.
      </p>

      <p>
        However, as Findlen, Edelstein and other humanities scholars experimented with the data through a range of case studies, including interactive visual representations of <a href="http://republicofletters.stanford.edu/casestudies/franklin/index.html">Benjamin Franklin</a>’s and <a href="http://republicofletters.stanford.edu/casestudies/locke/index.html">John Locke</a>’s social networks, they discovered the tools were lacking.
      </p>

      <p>
        “Almost all of the data visualization tools that are currently available have been designed with modern data sets in mind,” Edelstein said. Existing tools, such as those for statistical, literary and spatial analysis, “don’t work well for historical data, which tends to be messy and incomplete,” he added.
      </p>

      <p>
        <strong>NICOLE COLEMAN</strong>, the academic technology specialist who contributed to the development of each of the Mapping the Republic of Letters case studies, said that as she and the researchers built those visualizations they didn’t realize they were at the “beginning of a deep exploration of how to use graphical interfaces for humanistic inquiry.”
      </p>

      <p>
        <strong>Customized tools</strong>
      </p>

      <p>
        For example, to explore travel on the famed Grand Tour, the team created an interactive version of Joseph Priestley’s<em> A Chart of Biography. </em>Written in 1765, it traces significant figures throughout history and is one the earliest such timelines. With the digital version, scholars can pan and zoom, click through layers of information, and sort and filter according to any number of attributes associated with individuals represented in the database.
      </p>

      <p>
        Traditional computational visualization formats, like graphs, bar charts and scatterplots, can be abstract, but Coleman said customized tools contextualize fragmentary information and “make visible possible connections that are not otherwise in the data.”
      </p>

      <p>
        With this more nuanced representation of the data, the researchers “will be able to map not just the exchange of letters, but any type of location-associated data like place of birth, place of publication, travel, etc.,” Coleman said.
      </p>

      <p>
        The specialized suite of tools will be designed “so that anyone interested in history can easily use them,” said Edelstein. Open source modules, or “widgets,” will benefit all walks of researchers, from amateur historians to high school students, though Edelstein noted that scholars working on the Scientific Revolution and Enlightenment “will probably benefit the most from this work, since they can use the tools as well as the data, and even upload data sets of their own.”
      </p>

      <p>
        <em>—CORRIE GOLDMAN, <a href="http://humanexperience.stanford.edu">The Humanities at Stanford</a></em>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CESTA Crowdsourcing Projects in the Stanford News]]></title>
    <link href="/news/2013/05/23/cesta-crowdsourcing-projects-in-the-stanford-news/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-23T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/news/2013/05/23/cesta-crowdsourcing-projects-in-the-stanford-news</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You may find the following article on the web: <a href="http://stanford.io/16KRsTw">http://stanford.io/16KRsTw</a></p>

<p>May 21, 2013</p>

<h1>Stanford humanities scholars harness the power of crowdsourcing</h1>

<div>
  <p>
    Researchers at<strong> </strong>Stanford&#8217;s Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis are incorporating the knowledge and resources of the public into three digital humanities research projects.<em> </em>
  </p>
</div>

<p>By Corrie Goldman</p>

<p><img src="http://news.stanford.edu/pr/2013/images/crowds_worker_news.jpg" alt="" width="300" /></p>

<div>
  A Year of the Bay project officer scans and pins historical postcards at the California Historical Society exhibition. (Photo courtesy of The Stanford Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis)
</div>

<p>Over the years, garage sale and used bookstore aficionado Michael Rettie has discovered dozens of historical photographs in forgotten boxes.</p>

<p>A new crowdsourcing project organized by Stanford researchers is enabling Rettie to post his finds on a publicly accessible virtual map that offers a nuanced picture of San Francisco Bay area history.</p>

<p>Rettie is one of many amateur historical researchers contributing to <a href="http://www.historypin.com/project/13839007-YearoftheBay/#%7Cphotos/gallery/">Year of the Bay</a>, the first of three crowdsourcing experiments underway at Stanford.</p>

<p>Crowdsourcing holds the promise of enabling scholars &#8220;to engage people locally, across the country, and around the world in real research,&#8221; said <a href="http://history.stanford.edu/frank_zephyr">Zephyr Frank</a>, an associate professor of history and director of Stanford&#8217;s <a href="http://cesta.stanford.edu/">Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis</a> (CESTA), which is conducting the experiments with support from the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation.</p>

<p>While Year of the Bay seeks to tap a general audience for new historical sources, the <a href="http://crowdsourcingthehumanities.blogspot.com/">500 Novels</a> project is looking for a specific group: fans of British novels are being asked to help map how London was represented in 18<sup>th</sup>- and 19<sup>th</sup>-century literature.</p>

<p>The third project, <a href="http://crowdsourcingthehumanities.blogspot.com/">Living with Railroads,</a> connects amateur railroad buffs with scholars to test whether their different sources and interpretations can be combined to better understand the rapid expansion of railroad networks in the 19<sup>th</sup> century and how the railroads changed communities across the United States.</p>

<p>All three experiments bring together digital humanities scholars from Stanford&#8217;s Literary Lab and Spatial History Lab at CESTA, with colleagues at other universities, libraries, museums and archives. Stanford students are working on the projects as research assistants supported by the Office of the Vice-Provost for Undergraduate Education.</p>

<h3><strong>Big year for Bay Area</strong></h3>

<p>The Year of the Bay project aims to take advantage of big public events in the San Francisco Bay area in 2013 – the America&#8217;s Cup yacht races, the opening of a new span of the San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge, the 150<sup>th</sup> anniversary of the Port of San Francisco and dozens of commemorations at museums, libraries, and archives – to encourage people from diverse communities around the bay to share their different histories.</p>

<p>The endeavor also &#8220;seeks to test how well crowdsourcing initiatives can build upon the enthusiasm and interest created by local or regional events,&#8221; said <a href="http://christensenlab.net/">Jon Christensen</a>, an environmental historian at the University of California-Los Angeles who is working with CESTA on Year of the Bay.</p>

<p>Developed as a collaboration between Stanford researchers and <a href="http://www.historypin.com/">Historypin</a>, a nonprofit organization that facilitates the sharing of historical materials online, the Year of the Bay site was launched in April 2013 in conjunction with <a href="http://www.californiahistoricalsociety.org/exhibitions/">&#8220;Curating the Bay,&#8221;</a> an exhibition at the California Historical Society in San Francisco.</p>

<p>Year of the Bay has already attracted hundreds of submissions, both online and at the exhibition &#8220;pinning station&#8221; where visitors can add their own photographs and memories to the project during community events at the California Historical Society.</p>

<p>&#8220;We hope that crowdsourcing will enable us to give voice to the diverse ethnic communities around the bay and their experiences, which are often missing from historical archives,&#8221; said Christensen, who curated the exhibition, which is showing this spring and summer.</p>

<h3><strong>The crowdsourcing debate</strong></h3>

<p>Crowdsourcing appears to hold a great deal of potential for historians, but there is, however, great debate about the &#8220;usefulness of crowdsourcing for scholarly research,&#8221; Frank said, and &#8220;very little research on the best ways to engage the public in providing truly useful information in the process.&#8221;</p>

<p>Each of the Stanford crowdsourcing experiments seeks to &#8220;use technology to advance scholarly research through engaging the public beyond the walls of the university,&#8221; said Frank.</p>

<p>At the same time, he said, each experiment will &#8220;test how well crowdsourcing works with different communities and for different kinds of research problems.&#8221;</p>

<p>The three projects taken together, he added, will help scholars better understand both the possibilities and limitations of the use of crowdsourcing in the humanities.</p>

<p>Frank said the experiments are an important step in the development of the digital humanities.</p>

<p>&#8220;Computer technology offers powerful new tools for humanities research, and we&#8217;re taking advantage of them in all kinds of ways at Stanford,&#8221; he said. &#8220;Crowdsourcing has exciting potential for augmenting our research and scholarship in important ways. But technology and the crowd cannot replace the crucial humanistic work of critical analysis and interpretation. That&#8217;s why we have to do these experiments and carefully evaluate the results.&#8221;</p>

<p><em>Camille Brown, an intern with <em>[*the Human Experience</em>]<a href="http://humanexperience.stanford.edu/">8</a></em>, contributed to this story.*</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Diarna visits CESTA]]></title>
    <link href="/news/2013/05/14/diarna-visits-cesta/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/news/2013/05/14/diarna-visits-cesta</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Aron Rodrigue brought guests from the Diarna project to CESTA to share ideas about how to gather and share historical spatial data. <a href="http://diarna.org">Diarna</a> (&#8220;our homes&#8221; in judeo-arabic) is a Digital Heritage Mapping project and geo-museum dedicated to documenting important sites in Jewish life in the Middle East and North Africa.</p>

<div id="attachment_595" class="wp-caption alignnone" style="width: 310px">
  <a href="https://cesta.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Screen-Shot-2013-05-14-at-9.14.28-AM.png"><img class="size-medium wp-image-595" title="Dar Bishi Synagogue" src="https://cesta.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/Screen-Shot-2013-05-14-at-9.14.28-AM-300x172.png" alt="" width="300" height="172" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">
    From Diarna&#8217;s reconstruction of Dar Bishi Synagogue in Tripoli
  </p>
</div>

<p>Jason Guberman and Frances Malino showed us how they collect references to sites and images of sites from Google Books, Hathi Trust and other cultural heritage archives. They combine these resources with site visits to gather any remaining evidence of sites that either have been destroyed or are in danger of being destroyed. They collect personal accounts and photographs on site, then rapidly build 3D models based on surviving evidence to produce rich online exhibits that include Google Earth fly throughs, 360 degree views, photographs, video and audio and text.</p>

<p><a href="https://cesta.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/177__820x740_esther-banner.png"><img class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-593" title="177__820x740_esther-banner" src="https://cesta.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/2013/05/177__820x740_esther-banner-300x69.png" alt="" width="300" height="69" /></a></p>

<p>Not only are they constructing an extraordinarily rich archive, they are doing it with widely available tools: Trimble 3D warehouse, Sketchup, Picasa, YouTube, and 360 Cities.</p>

<p>Visit <a href="http://diarna.org">http://diarna.org</a></p>

<p>They are looking for volunteer researchers, videographers, translators, and 3D modelers (Sketchup). Contact<a href="mailto:info@diarna.org"> info@diarna.org</a>.</p>

<p>Attending: Aron Rodrigue (History, Stanford),  Frances Malino (History, Wellsley), Jason Guberman (Diarna), Zephyr Frank (CESTA), Nicole Coleman (CESTA)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[CESTA Crowdsourcing In the News:  History Experiment Uses Tech to Find New Stories]]></title>
    <link href="/news/2013/04/22/cesta-crowdsourcing-in-the-news-history-experiment-uses-tech-to-find-new-stories/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>/news/2013/04/22/cesta-crowdsourcing-in-the-news-history-experiment-uses-tech-to-find-new-stories</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.vcstar.com/news/2013/apr/20/history-experiment-uses-tech-to-find-new-stories/" target="_blank">Here is a recent article</a> on the Curating the Bay: Crowdsourcing a New Environmental History exhibit at the California Historical Society.</p>

<div id="attachment_569" class="wp-caption aligncenter" style="width: 617px">
  <a href="https://cesta.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/526dc005890845429159b63e1ab8992d-7431e2f158d6415590a78566b9c53b28-0_t607.jpg"><img class="size-full wp-image-569" title="526dc005890845429159b63e1ab8992d-7431e2f158d6415590a78566b9c53b28-0_t607" src="https://cesta.stanford.edu/wp-content/uploads/2013/04/526dc005890845429159b63e1ab8992d-7431e2f158d6415590a78566b9c53b28-0_t607.jpg" alt="" width="607" height="394" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">
    AP Photo/Eric Risberg
  </p>
</div>

<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>