<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis</title>
    <description>The Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis (CESTA) is comprised of the Spatial History Project, Humanities+Design, and the Literary Lab, the Poetic Media Lab, as well as Text Technologies and Chinese Railroad Workers. This interdisciplinary collective of labs operates independently of any one particular home department, and is organizationally housed within the Dean of Research at Stanford University.</description>
    <link></link>
    <atom:link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
      <item>
        <title>Digital Humanities Skills Workshop</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As part of Digital Humanities: Asia, Nicole Coleman and Jason Heppler are running a series of workshops at the Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis. If you are interested in learning more about Digital Humanities tools and techniques or want to prepare for the upcoming DHAsia workshops (&lt;a href=&quot;http://dhasia.org/&quot;&gt;http://dhasia.org/&lt;/a&gt;), bring a laptop and dig into the following sessions co-sponsored by CIDR, CESTA, and the DH Focal Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All sessions will be held at CESTA in rm 433A unless otherwise specified.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;DATA WRANGLING WITH PYTHON&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David McClure, a developer at the Library&amp;#39;s Center for Interdisciplinary Digital Research, will teach a two- part workshop to introduce techniques for cleaning and managing messy data with Python.
If you are interested in using Python for network analysis, you may be interested in the NetworkX workshop on 2/15.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part 1: Monday, January 11, 2 p.m. - 4 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part 2: Monday, January 25, 2 p.m. - 4 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;OMEKA&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jason Heppler, the ATS for History and member of CIDR will get you up and running with Omeka (&lt;a href=&quot;http://omeka.org/&quot;&gt;http://omeka.org/&lt;/a&gt;) an open source platform for digital publishing and exhibit building. If you are interested in Neatline, this workshop will familiarize you with the underlying platform.
Thursday, January 14, 2 p.m. - 4 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;NEATLINE&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;David McClure, one of the Neatline developers and now part of the CIDR team in the Library will take you through the process of building an interactive spatial and temporal exhibit with Neatline (&lt;a href=&quot;http://neatline.org/&quot;&gt;http://neatline.org/&lt;/a&gt;), a set of add on tools for Omeka. (See the 1/14 Omeka workshop above.)
Monday, February 1, 2 p.m.- 4 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;PALLADIO&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Digital Humanities Focal Group is hosting this introduction to Palladio, a suite of visualization tools for data exploration. (&lt;a href=&quot;http://palladio.designhumanities.org&quot;&gt;http://palladio.designhumanities.org&lt;/a&gt;) This workshop will take place in Building 260, Room 252.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monday, January 25, 12:00-1:30 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;NETWORKS&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The introductory session in this two-part series will show you how to prepare a data set for network analysis and then visualize that data set with Gephi and/or Cytoscape. We will also share examples of network analysis in humanities research. The second session, taught by Sebastian Ahnert, will provide an introduction to the Python package for network analysis, NetworkX. If you are not familiar with Python, the sessions taught by Dave McClure beginning January 11 will prepare you for this session.
Part 1, Introduction to Networks for Humanists: Monday, February 8, 2 p.m. - 4 p.m.
Part 2, Network Analysis and NetworkX: Monday, February 22, 2 p.m. - 4 p.m.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>//workshop/2016/01/12/dh-skills-workshop/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//workshop/2016/01/12/dh-skills-workshop/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Digital Humanities at Stanford</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://shc.stanford.edu/digital-humanities&quot;&gt;Stanford Humanities Center&lt;/a&gt; is highlighting some of the work being done by digital humanities scholars around Stanford University, including several members and associates of CESTA. The full collection of videos produced by SHC can be &lt;a href=&quot;http://shc.stanford.edu/video-category/digital-humanities&quot;&gt;found online&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Geography of the Post&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/K_Q2olSSk4Y&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Lacuna Stories&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/3JVu6n2SbCU&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Palladio&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/nUUVgWxeATs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Writing Rights&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ew7Ek-hNO18&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Text Technologies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/wQKmktxYcsc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Enchanting the Desert&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/P-6Ci1rGmQQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Çatalhöyük Living Archive&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/IycpOCdzTIc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 02 Jul 2015 13:47:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>//announcement/2015/07/02/digital-humanities-at-stanford/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//announcement/2015/07/02/digital-humanities-at-stanford/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Geospatial Narrative: Perspectives from the Humanities, Cartography and Geographic Information Science</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 7th, Stanford University Libraries&amp;#39; Center for Interdisciplinary Digital
Research (CIDR) welcomed David O&amp;#39;Sullivan, Associate Professor of Geography at
the University of California, Berkeley to the Stanford campus for two events:
a panel discussion on geospatial narrative at CESTA, and a guest lecture on
spatial simulation modeling. For an overview of the panel discussion held at
CESTA, see &lt;a href=&quot;https://digitalhumanities.stanford.edu/cidr-hosts-osullivan-geography-lecture-and-geospatial-narratives-workshop&quot;&gt;Karl Grossner&amp;#39;s
summary&lt;/a&gt;
of the events.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2015 13:43:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>//announcement/2015/06/08/geospatial-narrative-perspectives-from-the-humanities-cartography-and-geographic-information-science/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//announcement/2015/06/08/geospatial-narrative-perspectives-from-the-humanities-cartography-and-geographic-information-science/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Humanities + Digital at the Stanford Humanities Center</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;On May 5, 2015, the Stanford Humanities Center hosted a panel discussion featuring Zephyr Frank, Elaine Treharne, Paula Finland, Karl Grossner, Brian Johnsrud, and Jason Heppler. The webcast was recorded live at SHC where the scholars and experts discussed how digital tools are helping them explore complex questions in history, literature, archeology, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/uNtB6Sf5Kjc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 05 May 2015 13:53:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>//events/2015/05/05/humanities-plus-digital-at-the-stanford-humanities-center/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//events/2015/05/05/humanities-plus-digital-at-the-stanford-humanities-center/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>HIST205F Electronic Poster Session, December 1 at 3:15pm</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;You are cordially invited to attend the final presentations by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jasonheppler.org/teaching/hist205f.2014/&quot;&gt;HIST205F:
Digital History&lt;/a&gt; students!
The event is open to the public and I encourage you to pass this announcement
along to anyone who you feel would be interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students have, over the quarter, learned about the theory and method of
digital history and are applying those skills and ideas to the history of
Silicon Valley. The students have each conducted original research into the
Valley&amp;#39;s history or, in the case of the graduate students in the course, have
pursued their own research agendas. We are ending the class with a public
electronic poster session to allow the students to share their work and
receive feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The session is informal and meant for visitors to explore the projects and
talk to the students about their work. There&amp;#39;s no set schedule, so feel free
to come and go!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HIST205F Electronic Poster Session
Lathrop Library 190 (the old GSB building across from History Corner)
Monday, December 1, 3:15pm-5:00pm&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Light refreshments will be provided.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2014 09:55:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>//announcement/2014/11/25/hist205f-electronic-poster-session-december-1-at-3-15pm/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//announcement/2014/11/25/hist205f-electronic-poster-session-december-1-at-3-15pm/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Multimedia Publication: Mapping Mobility in the Budapest Ghetto</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with the United States Holocaust Memorial Museum (USHMM.org), the Spatial History Project is pleased to announce the release of an interactive multimedia publication entitled &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://web.stanford.edu/group/spatialhistory/cgi-bin/site/viz.php?id=411&amp;amp;project_id=&quot;&gt;Mapping Mobility in the Budapest Ghetto&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/budapest_preview.png&quot; alt=&quot;Mapping Mobility in the Budapest Ghetto&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project features research by historian &lt;strong&gt;Tim Cole&lt;/strong&gt; and geographer &lt;strong&gt;Alberto Giordano&lt;/strong&gt; of the Holocaust Geographies Collaborative, an international research group affiliated with the Spatial History Project.  The multimedia publication investigates news ways of understanding the experience and definition of the ghetto in 1944 Budapest. Combining traditional historical research methods with network analysis and computer simulation, we modeled how the Jewish population may have been distributed in the city. The resulting animation shows, moment by moment, how restrictions in space (where Jews could and could not live) and time (when Jews could leave their homes) created a distorted geography that led to different levels of mobility, access, and vulnerability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design and programming: &lt;strong&gt;Erik Steiner&lt;/strong&gt;
Audio Production: &lt;strong&gt;Sophia Paliza-Carre &amp;#39;13&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2014 14:21:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>//announcement/2014/06/27/new-multimedia-publication-mapping-mobility-in-the-budapest-ghetto/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//announcement/2014/06/27/new-multimedia-publication-mapping-mobility-in-the-budapest-ghetto/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New Article in Journal of American History</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The June 2014 issue of the &lt;em&gt;Journal of American History&lt;/em&gt; includes an article
written by CESTA researcher Cameron Blevins, &amp;quot;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jah.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/full/jau184?%0Aijkey=unucsImiwNrelaF&amp;amp;keytype=ref&quot;&gt;Space, Nation, and the Triumph
of Region: A View of the World from Houston&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;quot; In the first digital history
article published by the &lt;em&gt;Journal of American History&lt;/em&gt;, Blevins shows how new
technology can add to the historian&amp;#39;s toolkit and alter our understanding of
the historical production of space and region. He uses &amp;quot;distant reading&amp;quot; to
uncover surprising and otherwise hidden spatial patterns in how a Texas
newspaper crafted a view of the world for its readers in the late nineteenth
century. In an age of national integration the newspaper constructed an
imagined geography dominated by regional connections. Blevins conducted his
research at the Spatial History Lab, which has published &lt;a href=&quot;http://spatialhistory.stanford.edu/viewoftheworld&quot;&gt;an online
component&lt;/a&gt;
visualizing his findings and discussing the article&amp;#39;s digital foundation.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2014 09:49:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>//announcement/2014/05/30/new-article-in-journal-of-american-history/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//announcement/2014/05/30/new-article-in-journal-of-american-history/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Announcing the Graduate Certificate in Digital Humanities</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis (CESTA) at Stanford is proud to
announce a new graduate certificate in digital humanities program, starting fall
quarter 2014. Please see below for details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Graduate Certificate in Digital Humanities (GCDH) meets a growing need among
the humanities for training in digital methods by leveraging existing resources
at Stanford University.  The GCDH program will draw upon the community of
expertise in the Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis (CESTA).  Over the past
several years, dozens of graduate students have taken classes taught by CESTA
affiliated faculty and postdoctoral fellows, and participated in workshops and
seminars sponsored by CESTA. The CESTA Graduate Certificate in Digital
Humanities offers a formal structure for this activity and allows graduate
students to acquire and deepen their technical and conceptual skills as well as
to strengthen their position in the competitive job market within and beyond the
academy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GCDH seeks to strike a balance between the cultivation of technical skills
and their practical application within project-based Digital Humanities
research.  The program is meant to be relatively lightweight in terms of
specific requirements and flexible as to content and timing in order to best
support the work students are doing in their home departments.  Core classes and
exposure to the CESTA research community will ensure that students leave the
program with solid skills and the experience of learning in a cohort
environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Completion of the program will result in both a Certificate, signed by the CESTA
Director and the Chair of the doctoral student’s home department, and, through
the program, the student will also develop a digital portfolio suitable for the
job market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Pilot Plan: GCDH 2014-2017&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Course work&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students wishing to take part in the first cohort starting in 2014-15 and
thereafter will be expected to complete one GCDH-approved graduate core course
for a letter grade, and one additional approved elective course.  The approved
core courses for the first year of the program are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spatial History (HIST 401a)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Literary Lab (ENG 303C)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Humanities+Design (DLCL 202)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Students who have completed any of the core courses, or equivalent courses
taught by members of the program, in past years are eligible to move forward to
the next step in the GCDH program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following or concurrent with the completion of the required core course,
students must complete the following two certificate components:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Additional coursework (1 or more classes, may be taken pass/fail, must be
approved in advance by the committee in charge) in computer science, information
design, statistics, network analysis, linguistics, or other fields approved by
the student&amp;#39;s supervisor and the CESTA committee in charge. A list of course
recommendations is forthcoming.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Independent research project and portfolio including a finished project
which will be evaluated and approved by both an Academic Council supervisor and
be accepted as an affiliated project in one of CESTA’s labs.  The duration of
such projects must be a minimum of 1 academic quarter. Students may take up to
5 units of credit as directed reading for the purpose of completing the
independent research project.  Final projects will be included in the student’s
e-portfolio and published on the CESTA website.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Supervised collaborative research in a CESTA lab with the expectation that the
student’s participation culminates in a DH product substantially of the
authorship of the student—2 quarters minimum duration. The student’s portion of
the research will be included in the e-portfolio and published on the CESTA
website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Staffing:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The GCDH program is staffed primarily by CESTA. Core faculty include Mark
Algee-Hewitt, Franco Moretti, Richard White, Dan Edelstein, Paula Findlen,
Giovanna Ceserani, Walter Scheidel, Elaine Treharne, Amir Eschel, and Zephyr
Frank. Affiliated CESTA faculty include Allyson Hobbs, Edith Scheffer, Caroline
Winterer, Mark McGurl, Ana Minian, and Mikael Wolfe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical expertise is provided by CESTA staff members and the extended CESTA
community. Included in this group are the following: Celena Allen (GIS), Erik
Steiner (visualization design and cartography), Ryan Heuser (programming),
Nicole Coleman (information design and visualization), and Jason Heppler
(digital history). Beyond the core staff and affiliates, the program will draw
upon the expertise of Elijah Meeks (information design) and Karl Grossner
(information design and cartography).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To Apply:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Admission to the program is on a rolling basis, and students may apply at any
time. Please submit a letter of interest and any supporting information to CESTA
Lab Manager Matt Bryant,
&lt;a href=&quot;mattbryant.stanford@gmail.com&quot;&gt;mailto:mattbryant.stanford@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;. For more
information about the new GDCH program or CESTA in general, please see
&lt;a href=&quot;http://cesta.stanford.edu&quot;&gt;http://cesta.stanford.edu&lt;/a&gt; or contact Matt at the
email above.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2014 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>//announcement/2014/05/14/dh-certificate/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//announcement/2014/05/14/dh-certificate/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>CESTA/Spatial History Project is Hiring Undergraduate Research Assistants for Winter Quarter</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The Spatial History Project within the Center for Spatial and Textual Analysis (CESTA) at Stanford seeks to hire undergraduate Research Assistants to work on a variety of digital projects based in humanities scholarship at the nexus of history, English, art, and geography. We seek students who bring practical knowledge or interest in information design and the development of interactive visualization tools for humanities research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Successful candidates will have a strong background or interest in learning in any of the following areas:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Information visualization and design (e.g. graphic design, cartography, programming, interaction design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Adobe CS, JavaScript, ActionScript d3, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Spatial and network analysis (GIS, Tableau, Gephi, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;  Archival research, data analysis, database creation and management&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Examples of possible projects that new research assistants could be involved are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Living with the Railroads&lt;/strong&gt;
Following the work of Richard White, Living with the Railroads seeks to use crowdsourcing to learn more about the social, cultural, and environmental impact of the development and expansion of the railroads in the American West, and hopefully eventually across the United States. The goal, in conjunction with Historypin, is to get railroad enthusiasts to upload their data, identify images and documents whose provenance is unknown, and help facilitate the growth of connections between enthusiast and enthusiast communities, while at the same time collecting metadata on these images.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Chinese Railroad Workers&lt;/strong&gt;
Faculty Gordon Chang (History) and Shelley Fisher Fishkin (English) are leading this project to unearth the undocumented history of the Chinese workers who constructed the U.S. transcontinental railroad in the late 1860s. This project seeks to discover and present this missing history from many different sources. Participants from a wide range of backgrounds, disciplines, and locations are working together to piece this history together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Geography of the Post&lt;/strong&gt;
From the end of the Civil War until the close of the nineteenth century, the United States Postal System grew into a vast communications network. The Post was one of the century&amp;#8217;s largest spatial systems, with more than 75,000 offices connecting communities scattered across the continent. Geography of the Post maps this behemoth network on its western periphery: where it spread, how it operated, and its role in shaping the space and place of the region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Law of the Antebellum Frontier&lt;/strong&gt;
Innovative digital research technologies allow us to look at the expansion of the American nation during the critical years before the Civil War in new ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Microhistory of the Great Migration The Great Migration&lt;/strong&gt; was a watershed in African American life: over the course of six decades (1910-1970), six million black southerners left the South in search of more meaningful experiences of freedom. This project hopes to offer a different angle of vision on the migration by bringing to light the places where migrants slept, ate, got haircuts, and danced along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rebooting History&lt;/strong&gt;
This project is an exploration with a point of origin in how regional utilization of East Palo Alto&amp;#8217;s space helped set the stage for a dynamic of inequality between the community and what would become Silicon Valley.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Genealogy of Desert Ant Colonies&lt;/strong&gt; Over the past 3 decades, Gordon has studied the behavior, demography and ecology of a population of about 300 harvester ant colonies in Arizona, using both field and laboratory experiments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working hours are flexible, with a target of 8-10 hours per week. RAs will join an exciting community of scholars including undergraduates, graduate students, post-docs, and faculty. RAs will have the opportunity to co-author projects and potentially include their own work in their portfolio. In addition to technical skills, RAs must demonstrate past success in creative problem solving, and a devotion to teamwork.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please send your resume and a cover letter explaining your qualifications to Matt Bryant (&lt;a href=&quot;mailto:mattbryant.stanford@gmail.com&quot;&gt;mattbryant.stanford@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;) no later than &lt;strong&gt;noon on Monday, December 2nd.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please share this announcement with anyone who you feel might be interested.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 22 Nov 2013 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>//announcement/2013/11/22/cestaspatial-history-project-is-hiring-undergraduate-research-assistants-for-winter-quarter/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//announcement/2013/11/22/cestaspatial-history-project-is-hiring-undergraduate-research-assistants-for-winter-quarter/</guid>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>CESTA Presents Christopher Richard &amp;#8211; Myth Busting the Founding of San Francisco &amp;#8211; Dec. 2nd @ Noon</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Myth Busting the Founding of San Francisco – The Anza Expedition and the Role of Aquatic Habitats in the Siteing of Mission Dolores&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Monday, December 2nd @ Noon
Rm. 433A, Fourth Floor of Wallenberg Hall&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: small;&quot;&gt;Juan Bautista de Anza chose the locations for the mission and presidio in San Francisco in March 1776. Anza and his chaplain, Fr. Font, spent three days analyzing the agricultural and strategic potential of the various neighborhoods of San Francisco before siteing the mission and presidio. They gave the name &lt;em&gt;Dolors &lt;/em&gt;to the water supply that they expected to provide for agriculture at the mission. Three months later when the settlers arrived, the writings of the pastor, Fr. Palou, reinterpreted the water feature named Dolores.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: small;&quot;&gt;This engendered a long-standing controversy about the pre-European terrain of San Francisco, the analysis of which touches upon tales which, while incorrect, are held as legend. This adds an epistemological challenge to righting the record, not present in most presentations of research. In this case, the first-person journals were detailed, sophisticated, and in agreement, however challenged in narrative structure. The controversy is largely traceable to a mis-translation/interpretation in the 1860s, which blossomed into controversy at the centennial in 1876, and which is hotly contested to this day. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: small;&quot;&gt;A succession of maps from the Land-Case collection at the Bancroft Library, newly brought into the discussion, along with the extreme geomorphic unlikelihood of the legendary version, make a clear case for a revised history of the event and terrain.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: small;&quot;&gt;Christopher Richard is a recently retired curator of aquatic biology at Oakland Museum of California. During 30 years at the museum he curated two major permanent gallery expansions and a dozen temporary exhibitions. The majority of his research was heading a team mapping the modern and historic hydrology of urbanized portions of the S.F. Bay Area, resulting in 15 published maps. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: small;&quot;&gt; Since 2006, he has been studying the records of the Anza expeditions to California in the 1770s. These provide valuable baseline descriptions of aquatic habitats prior to significant modification by European influence. He is in the process of revisiting all the sites described by Anza to determine the relative health of the remaining aquatic habitats.&lt;span style=&quot;font-family: Times New Roman,Times,serif;&quot;&gt;&lt;br /&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2013 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>//2013/11/01/cesta-presents-christopher-richard-myth-busting-the-founding-of-san-francisco-dec-2nd-noon/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">//2013/11/01/cesta-presents-christopher-richard-myth-busting-the-founding-of-san-francisco-dec-2nd-noon/</guid>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>